{
  "title": "Theory_of_Computation - Context_Free_Grammar — Slot 3 (11 Questions)",
  "duration": 30,
  "sections": [
    {
      "name": "Context_Free_Grammar — Slot 3",
      "questions": [
        {
          "id": 1,
          "question": "<p>Which of the following grammar rules violate the requirements of an operator grammar? P, Q, R are\nnonterminals, and r,s,t are terminals.  <br> \\((i)P\\rightarrow QR \\)  <br> \\( (ii)P\\rightarrow QsR \\)  <br> \\( (iii)P\\rightarrow \\varepsilon \\)  <br> \\( (iv)P\\rightarrow QtRr \\) <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2004)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>(i) only</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>(i) and (iii) only</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>(ii) and (iii) only</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>(iii) and (iv) only</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>B.</b> <p>(i) and (iii) only</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/1005/gate2004-8#a_list\" targer=\"_blank\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 2,
          "question": "<p>Consider the grammar shown below. <br>\nS \\(\\rightarrow\\) C C <br>\nC \\(\\rightarrow\\) cC | d <br>\nThe grammar is <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2003)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>LL(1)</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>LALR (1) but not SLR (1)</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>SLR (1) but not LL (1)</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>LR (1) but not LALR (1)</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>A.</b> <p>LL(1)</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/945/gate2003-57#a_list\" targer=\"_blank\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 3,
          "question": "<p>Let G = ({S}, {a, b} R, S) be a context free grammar where the rule set R is \\(S\\rightarrow aSb|SS|\\epsilon\\)<br>\nWhich of the following statements is true? <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2003)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>G is not ambiguous</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>There exist x, y, \\(\\in\\) L (G) such that xy \\(\\notin\\) L(G)</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>There is a deterministic pushdown automaton that accepts L(G)</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>We can find a deterministic finite state automaton that accepts L(G)</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>C.</b> <p>There is a deterministic pushdown automaton that accepts L(G)</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/940/gate2003-51#a_list\" targer=\"_blank\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 4,
          "question": "<p>Which of the following suffices to convert an arbitrary CFG to an LL(1) grammar? <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2003)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>Removing left recursion alone</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>Factoring the grammar alone</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>Removing left recursion and factoring the grammar</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>None of this</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>D.</b> <p>None of this</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/906/gate2003-16#a_list\" targer=\"_blank\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 5,
          "question": "<p>Consider the following decision problems:\n<br><br>\n(P1): Does a given finite state machine accept a given string?<br>(P2): Does a given context free grammar generate an infinite number of strings?<br><br>Which of the following statements is true? <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2000)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>Both(P1) and (P2) are decidable</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>Neither (P1) nor (P2) is decidable</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>Only (P1) is decidable</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>Only (P2) is decidable</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>A.</b> <p>Both(P1) and (P2) are decidable</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/656/gate2000-2-9\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 6,
          "question": "<p>Consider a grammar with the following productions<br>\n\\(S \\rightarrow a \\alpha b \\mid b \\alpha c \\mid aB\\)<br>\n\\(S \\rightarrow \\alpha S\\mid b\\)<br>\n\\(S \\rightarrow \\alpha b b\\mid ab\\)<br>\n\\(S \\alpha \\rightarrow bd b\\mid b\\)<br>\nThe above grammar is: <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 1995)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>Context free</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>Regular</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>Context sensitive</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>LR(k)</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>D.</b> <p>LR(k)</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/2597/gate1995-1-10\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 7,
          "question": "<p>Which of the following features cannot be captured by context-free grammars? <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 1994)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>Syntax of if-then-else statements</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>Syntax of recursive procedures</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>Whether a variable has been declared before its use</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>Variable names of arbitrary length</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>C.</b> <p>Whether a variable has been declared before its use</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/2461/gate1994-1-18\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 8,
          "question": "<p>Choose the correct alternatives (more than one may be correct) and write the corresponding letters only: <br>\nIf G is a context free grammar and w is a string of length l in L(G), how long is a derivation of w in G, if G is in Chomsky normal form? <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 1992)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>2l</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>2l+1</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>2l-1</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>l</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>C.</b> <p>2l-1</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/576/gate1992-02-xviii\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 9,
          "question": "<p>Choose the correct alternatives (more than one may be correct ) and write the corresponding letters only:<br>\nConsider the SLR(1) and LALR (1)  parsing tables for a context free grammar. Which of the following statement is/are true? <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 1992)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>The goto part of both tables may be different.</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>The shift entries are identical in both the tables.</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>The reduce entries in the tables may be different.</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>The error entries in tables may be different</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>B.</b> <p>The shift entries are identical in both the tables.</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/571/gate1992-02-xiv\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 10,
          "question": "<p>Choose the correct alternatives (more than one may be correct) and write the corresponding letters only:<br>For a context free grammar, FOLLOW(A) is the set of terminals that can appear immediately to the right of non-terminal A in some \"sentential\" form. We define two sets LFOLLOW(A) and RFOLLOW(A) by replacing the word \"sentential\" by \"left sentential\" and \"right most sentential\" respectively in the definition of FOLLOW (A). <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 1992)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>FOLLOW(A) and LFOLLOW(A) may be different.</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>FOLLOW(A) and RFOLLOW(A) are always the same.</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>All the three sets are identical.</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>All the three sets are different.</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>A.</b> <p>FOLLOW(A) and LFOLLOW(A) may be different.</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/570/gate1992-02-xiii\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 11,
          "question": "<p>A context-free grammar is ambiguous if: <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 1987)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>The grammar contains useless non-terminals.</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>It produces more than one parse tree for some sentence.</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>Some production has two non terminals side by side on the right-hand side.</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>None of the above.</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>B.</b> <p>It produces more than one parse tree for some sentence.</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/80291/gate1987-1-xii\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        }
      ]
    }
  ]
}